I study how the brain processes
أنا أدرس كيفية معالجة الدماغ
information. That is, how it takes
للمعلومات .. أي كيفية استقباله
information in from the outside world, and
للمعلومات من العال الخارجي
converts it into patterns of electrical activity,
ويحولها الى شفرات من الاشارات الكهربائية
and then how it uses those patterns
ومن ثم كيف يستخدم هذه الشفرات
to allow you to do things --
للسماح لنا
to see, hear, to reach for an object.
بالرؤية والاستماع و لمس الاشياء
So I'm really a basic scientist, not
في الحقيقة انا عالمة
a clinician, but in the last year and a half
ولست بطبيبة .. ولكن في السنة والنصف الماضية
I've started to switch over, to use what
بدأت أغير مجالي لكي أستخدم
we've been learning about these patterns
ما تعلمته عن تلك الشفرات
of activity to develop prosthetic devices,
من اجل تطوير الاجهزة الحسية المعطوبة
and what I wanted to do today is show you
وما أريد ان اريكم اياه اليوم
an example of this.
هو مثال عن ذلك
It's really our first foray into this.
انه في الحقيقة العرض الاول لهذه الفكرة
It's the development of a prosthetic device
انه تطوير لجهاز صناعي
for treating blindness.
لمعالجة العمي
So let me start in on that problem.
دعوني أولا اتحدث في لب المشكلة
There are 10 million people in the U.S.
هناك 10 ملايين شخص مصاب بالعمى في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
and many more worldwide who are blind
وهناك اكثر من هذا بكثير حول العالم
or are facing blindness due to diseases
وهم مصابون بالعمى تبعاً لأمراض
of the retina, diseases like
اصابت الشبكية من مثل
macular degeneration, and there's little
التنكس البقعي و لا يوجد الكثير مما يمكننا القيام به
that can be done for them.
حيالهم
There are some drug treatments, but
هناك بعض الادوية
they're only effective on a small fraction
ولكنها فعالة فقط على نسبة قليلة منهم
of the population. And so, for the vast
ولكن من اجل الاغلبية
majority of patients, their best hope for
فان معظمهم تشكل الاجهزة الصناعية
regaining sight is through prosthetic devices.
افضل امل لهم من اجل استرجاع البصر
The problem is that current prosthetics
ولكن المشكلة ان الاجهزة الصناعية الحالية
don't work very well. They're still very
لا تعمل بشكل جيد فهي ماتزال
limited in the vision that they can provide.
توفر رؤية محدودة
And so, you know, for example, with these
فعلى سبيل المثال يمكن للمصابون بالعمي
devices, patients can see simple things
بواسطة الاجهزة الصناعية ان يروا الامور البسيطة
like bright lights and high contrast edges,
مثل الاضواء الباهرة او الحواف متباينة الالوان
not very much more, so nothing close
وهذا ليس بالكثير .. وهو امر بعيد عن
to normal vision has been possible.
الرؤية الطبيعية التي كانت لديهم
So what I'm going to tell you about today
وما اريد ان اخبركم به اليوم
is a device that we've been working on
هو جهاز كنا نعمل عليه
that I think has the potential to make
واعتقد انه يملك الامكانية
a difference, to be much more effective,
بان يصنع فارقاً فعالاً في ذلك المجال
and what I wanted to do is show you
وما اريد ان افعله الان هو ان اريكم
how it works. Okay, so let me back up a
كيفية عمله .. ولكن دعوني اسهب أكثر
little bit and show you how a normal retina
عن كيفية عمل الشبكية الطبيعية
works first so you can see the problem
من اجل ان تفطنوا للمشكلة
that we were trying to solve.
التي نحاول حلها
Here you have a retina.
هنا ترون الشبكية
So you have an image, a retina, and a brain.
لدينا صورة .. شبكية .. و دماغ
So when you look at something, like this image
لذا عندما تنظر الي شيء مثل هذه الصورة
of this baby's face, it goes into your eye
لوجه هذا الطفل .. يدخل الضوء من خلال عينيك
and it lands on your retina, on the front-end
ومن ثم يصل الى الشبكية على الخلايا
cells here, the photoreceptors.
الامامية هنا " المبصرات "
Then what happens is the retinal circuitry,
وما يحدث حينها تقوم الشبكية الكهربائية
the middle part, goes to work on it,
في الجزء الاوسط بالعمل على تلك الاشعة
and what it does is it performs operations
وما تقوم به عبر عدة عمليات
on it, it extracts information from it, and it
هو استخراج المعلومات
converts that information into a code.
وتحويلها الى شفرة
And the code is in the form of these patterns
والشفرة تشبه هذا النمط
of electrical pulses that get sent
من النبضات الكهربائية التي ترسل
up to the brain, and so the key thing is
الى الدماغ .. لذا فمحور عملية البصر هنا
that the image ultimately gets converted
هو ان الصورة تتحول بصورة دائمة
into a code. And when I say code,
الى شفرة وعندما اقول شفرة
I do literally mean code.
فانا اعني حقا المعنى الحرفي للشفرة
Like this pattern of pulses here actually means "baby's face,"
مثل هذا النمط من النبضات الذي يمثل صورة وجه الطفل
and so when the brain gets this pattern
وعندما يستقبل دماغك هذا النمط
of pulses, it knows that what was out there
من النبضات .. يحلل ويعلم ما يوجد امامه
was a baby's face, and if it
ويميزه كوجه طفل وان كان
got a different pattern it would know
استقبل نمط اخر من النبضات ستكون الاستجابة مختلفة
that what was out there was, say, a dog,
كان يكون هناك كلب
or another pattern would be a house.
او منزل فالانماط ستتجاوب مع تلك الاختلافات
Anyway, you get the idea.
أتمنى ان تكون الفكرة قد وصلت
And, of course, in real life, it's all dynamic,
وطبعا في الحياة الاعتيادية تكون العملية ديناميكية
meaning that it's changing all the time,
اعني ان الصور تتغير باستمرار
so the patterns of pulses are changing
وانماط النبضات تتجواب مع ذلك التغير باستمرار
all the time because the world you're
طيلة الوقت لان العالم
looking at is changing all the time too.
الذي نعيش فيه يتغير طيلة الوقت ايضاً
So, you know, it's sort of a complicated
لذا كما ترون الامر معقد
thing. You have these patterns of pulses
لاننا نملك هذا النمط من النبضات
coming out of your eye every millisecond
التي تخرج من أعيننا كل ميلي ثانية
telling your brain what it is that you're seeing.
وتخبر الدماغ ما الذي نراه
So what happens when a person
ولكن ماذا يحدث مع الشخص
gets a retinal degenerative disease like
حينما يصاب بمرض في الشبكية
macular degeneration? What happens is
مثل التنكس البقعي ؟ .. ما يحدث هو
is that, the front-end cells die,
ان الخلايا الامامية تموت
the photoreceptors die, and over time,
وتموت المبصرات .. وعبر الزمن
all the cells and the circuits that are
الخلايا الكهربائية التي تنتج النبضات
connected to them, they die too.
والتي تتصل مع الخلايا تموت ايضا
Until the only things that you have left
حتى يبقى شيء واحد فحسب
are these cells here, the output cells,
وهو هذه الخلايا .. الخلايا التي تصدر المخرجات
the ones that send the signals to the brain,
والاشارات الى الدماغ
but because of all that degeneration
وبسبب المرض والتنكس
they aren't sending any signals anymore.
فهي لا ترسل اي اشارات
They aren't getting any input, so
بسبب عدم وجود مدخلات
the person's brain no longer gets
وعليه فان دماغ الفرد لم يعد يستقبل
any visual information --
اي معلومات بصرية
that is, he or she is blind.
وهذا يعني ان الشخص بات مصاب بالعمى
So, a solution to the problem, then,
والحل لهذه المشكلة اذا
would be to build a device that could mimic
هو ان نبني جهاز يحاكي
the actions of that front-end circuitry
عمل الخلايا الامامية " المبصرات "
and send signals to the retina's output cells,
ونقوم بارسال اشارات لمخرجات الشبكية
and they can go back to doing their
ومن ثم يمكنها ان تعود
normal job of sending signals to the brain.
الى عملها الطبيعي فترسل الاشارات الى الدماغ
So this is what we've been working on,
وهذا ما كنا نعمل عليه
and this is what our prosthetic does.
وهذا ما يقوم به جهازنا الصناعي
So it consists of two parts, what we call
انه يتكون من جزئين .. يمكننا ان نطلق تسمية
an encoder and a transducer.
مشفر بيانات .. و محول بيانات
And so the encoder does just
والمشفر يقوم بمحاكاة تماما
what I was saying: it mimics the actions
ما تحدثث لكم عنه
of the front-end circuitry -- so it takes images
والذي تقوم به الخلايا الامامية انه يستقبل الصور
in and converts them into the retina's code.
ويقوم بتحويلها الى شفرة الشبكية
And then the transducer then makes the
ومن ثم يقوم محول البيانات
output cells send the code on up
بجعل خلايا المخرجات ترسل الشفرة
to the brain, and the result is
الى الدماغ والنتيجة هي
a retinal prosthetic that can produce
جهاز شبكية صناعي يمكنه
normal retinal output.
ان يولد مخرجات بصرية طبيعية
So a completely blind retina,
اي شبكية مصابة بالعمى تماما
even one with no front-end circuitry at all,
وحتى ان لم تكن تملك الخلايا الامامية المبصرة على الاطلاق
no photoreceptors,
وبدون مبصرات
can now send out normal signals,
يمكنها الان ان تعود لمزاولة عملها وترسل شيفرات طبيعية
signals that the brain can understand.
شيفرات يمكن للدماغ من ان يفهمها
So no other device has been able
لا يوجد جهاز آخر يمكنه
to do this.
القيام بذلك
Okay, so I just want to take
حسناً .. أريد فحسب ان اتحدث
a sentence or two to say something about
بجملة او اثنتين عن هذا الامر
the encoder and what it's doing, because
اقصد عن المشفر و وظيفته
it's really the key part and it's
لانه العنصر الاهم
sort of interesting and kind of cool.
وهو امرٌ مثير و ممتع
I'm not sure "cool" is really the right word, but
لا اظن ان كلمة ممتع هي الكلمة الملائمة لذلك
you know what I mean.
تعلمون ما اقصده
So what it's doing is, it's replacing
وما نقوم به هو إستبدال
the retinal circuitry, really the guts of
دارة الشبكية .. دارة
the retinal circuitry, with a set of equations,
الشبكية ذاتها بمجموعة من المعادلات
a set of equations that we can implement
التي يمكن برمجتها وتطبيقها
on a chip. So it's just math.
على شريحة الكترونية .. ان الامر متعلق بالرياضيات فحسب
In other words, we're not literally replacing
بعبارة اخرى .. نحن لا نقوم حرفيا باستبدال
the components of the retina.
عناصر الشبكية
It's not like we're making a little mini-device
والامر ليس وكأننا نصنع جهاز مصغر
for each of the different cell types.
لكل جزء من اجزاء الخلية
We've just abstracted what the
نحن فقط نقوم فقط استنساخ
retina's doing with a set of equations.
ما تقوم به الشبكية بواسطة مجموعة من المعادلات
And so, in a way, the equations are serving
بصورة ما المعادلات تمثل ما يمكن
as sort of a codebook. An image comes in,
القول عنه انه دفتر شفرات .. حيث تصل الصورة
goes through the set of equations,
عبر عدة مجموعات من المعادلات
and out comes streams of electrical pulses,
ومن ثم يتم بثها عبر تيار نبضات كهربائية
just like a normal retina would produce.
كما تقوم به الشبكية تماما
Now let me put my money
والان دعوني أريكم مربط الفرس
where my mouth is and show you that
لما كنت اقوله
we can actually produce normal output,
وكيف انه بالامكان ان ننتج مخرجات طبيعة
and what the implications of this are.
وماهي تبعات ذلك
Here are three sets of
هذه ثلاث نماذج
firing patterns. The top one is from
من الانماط .. الاول من الاعلى
a normal animal, the middle one is from
هو نمط معين لكائن بصير .. والوسط
a blind animal that's been treated with
هو نمط لجهاز بصري لكائن مصاب بالعمى تم معالجته
this encoder-transducer device, and the
بواسطة جهاز المشفر والناقل
bottom one is from a blind animal treated
والثالث هو لكائن أعمى
with a standard prosthetic.
يتم معالجته بالاجهزة البديلة الصناعية
So the bottom one is the state-of-the-art
وكما ترون في الاسفل انه النمط الموجود
device that's out there right now, which is
الان في الاسواق والذي يتكون في الاساس
basically made up of light detectors,
من مستقبلات ضوئية
but no encoder. So what we did was we
ولكن بدون مشفر .. ولكن ما قمنا به
presented movies of everyday things --
هو اننا عرضنا افلاما عن حياتنا الاعتيادية
people, babies, park benches,
تتضمن الافراد و الاطفال و الحدائق
you know, regular things happening -- and
كما تعلمون امورا اعتيادية تحدث من حولنا
we recorded the responses from the retinas
وقمنا بتسجيل استجابة الشبكية لكل تلك المشاهل
of these three groups of animals.
تبعا للحالات الثلاث السابقة للكائن المدروس
Now just to orient you, each box is showing
ولكي أوضح لكم .. كل مستطيل
the firing patterns of several cells,
يوضح الاشارات والانماط لعدة خلايا
and just as in the previous slides,
وكما في اللوحة السابقة
each row is a different cell,
كل صف يمثل خلية مختلفة
and I just made the pulses a little bit smaller
وقد قمت بتوضح النبض بصورة اصغر
and thinner so I could show you
واضيق من اجل ان اتمكن من عرضه عليكم
a long stretch of data.
على مدى حزمة طويلة
So as you can see, the firing patterns
وكما ترون الشفرات التي يتم اخراجها
from the blind animal treated with
من الكائن الاعمى المعالج
the encoder-transducer really do very
بواسطة المشفر والناقل هي تقريبا مماثلة
closely match the normal firing patterns --
تماما لتلك التي تخرج من الكائن
and it's not perfect, but it's pretty good --
السليم . انها ليست مثالية ولكنها جيدة حقاً
and the blind animal treated with
واما عن تلك التي تخرج من الكائن الاعمى
the standard prosthetic,
والمعالج بجهاز صناعي اعتيادي
the responses really don't.
ليست بتلك الجودة
And so with the standard method,
فيما يحدث في الطريقة الاعتيادية
the cells do fire, they just don't fire
هو ان الخلايا تطلق فعلا الانماط
in the normal firing patterns because
ولكنها لا تطلق الانماط الصحيحة
they don't have the right code.
لانها لا تستقبل الشفرات الصحيحة
How important is this?
ولكن ما اهمية هذا ؟
What's the potential impact
وما هي تبعاته المترتبة
on a patient's ability to see?
على قدرة المريض على ان يرى ؟
So I'm just going to show you one
سوف أريكم الآن
bottom-line experiment that answers this,
خلاصة الابحاث التي تجيب على ذلك
and of course I've got a lot of other data,
بالطبع لدي الكثير من الابحاث والمعلومات
so if you're interested I'm happy
لذا ان كنتم مهتمين سوف أريكم بسعادة
to show more. So the experiment
اكثر من هذا .. التجربة
is called a reconstruction experiment.
تدعى تجربة اعادة البناء
So what we did is we took a moment
ما فعلنا هو اننا اخذنا لحظة زمنية
in time from these recordings and asked,
من هذه التسجيلات وطرحنا تساؤلاً
what was the retina seeing at that moment?
ما الذي تراه الشبكية في هذه اللحظة ؟
Can we reconstruct what the retina
هل يمكننا ان نعيد بناء ما تراه الشبكية
was seeing from the responses
بسبب الاستجابات
from the firing patterns?
الناتجة عن الانماط التي تنتج تبعا لها ؟
So, when we did this for responses
عندما قمنا بهذا حيال الاستجابات
from the standard method and from
من المفهوم الاساسي .. استطعنا صناعة
our encoder and transducer.
المشفر و الناقل
So let me show you, and I'm going to
دعوني أريكم .. وسوف أبدأ ..
start with the standard method first.
بالمفهوم الاساسي الاول
So you can see that it's pretty limited,
كما ترون ان الامر هنا محدود تقريباً
and because the firing patterns aren't
ولان الانماط الصادرة
in the right code, they're very limited in
ليست هي الشفرة الصحيحة .. فالنتائج محدودة
what they can tell you about
وما يمكنهم ان يقولوا
what's out there. So you can see that
حيال ما يرونه .. هو انهم
there's something there, but it's not so clear
يرون شيئاً ولكن ليس على درجة من الوضوح
what that something is, and this just sort of
لكي يميزوا ما هو هذا الامر .. وهذا يعود
circles back to what I was saying in the
بنا الى ما كنت اقوله
beginning, that with the standard method,
في البداية فيما يخص المفهوم الاساسي
patients can see high-contrast edges, they
حيث المرضى يرون الحواف و التمايز فيما بينها
can see light, but it doesn't easily go
ويرون الضوء ولكن لا يستطيعون بسهولة
further than that. So what was
تميز ما هو ادق من هذا
the image? It was a baby's face.
اذا ماهي تلك الصورة ؟ انها صورة وجه الطفل
So what about with our approach,
ولكن ماذا عن طريقتها
adding the code? And you can see
باضافة الشفرة ؟ فسوف ترى
that it's much better. Not only can you
ليس فقط افضل بكثير
tell that it's a baby's face, but you can
وليس فقط تستطيع تميز وجه الطفل ولكن
tell that it's this baby's face, which is a
يمكنك ان تميز لمن وجه الطفل هذا بسبب دقة التفاصيل
really challenging task.
وهي مهمة صعبة للغاية
So on the left is the encoder
حسناً . على الجهة اليسرى ترون المشفر
alone, and on the right is from an actual
وعلى اليمين ترون
blind retina, so the encoder and the transducer.
صورة الشبكية المصابة بالعمى .. حسناً المشفر و المحول هنا
But the key one really is the encoder alone,
ولكن الامر المحوري هو وجود المشفر بعيداً
because we can team up the encoder with
لاننا يجب ان نصل المشفر
the different transducer.
مع المحول الآخر
This is just actually the first one that we tried.
انها التجربة الاولى التي قمنا بها
I just wanted to say something about the standard method.
اريد فقط ان اقول شيئاً عن المفهوم الاساسي
When this first came out, it was just a really
عندما صدر هذا اولاً .كان الامر
exciting thing, the idea that you
مشوقاً للغاية .. فكرة انه
even make a blind retina respond at all.
يمكن لشخص مصاب العمى بسبب شبكية معطوبة ان يتجاوب كانت فكرة رائعة
But there was this limiting factor,
ولكن كان هناك عامل يقوض هذا الامر
the issue of the code, and how to make
وهو مشكلة الشفرة .. وكيف يمكننا
the cells respond better,
توليده وتتجاوب الخلايا معه بصورة افضل
produce normal responses,
لتنتج استجابات طبيعية
and so this was our contribution.
وكانت هنا مساهمتنا في هذا النطاق
Now I just want to wrap up,
الان يجب ان الخص الامر كله
and as I was mentioning earlier
وكما اخبرتكم من قبل
of course I have a lot of other data
لدي الكثير من المعلومات
if you're interested, but I just wanted to give
ان كنتم مهتمين .. فسوف اعطيتها اياكم
this sort of basic idea
انها معلومات اولية
of being able to communicate
تخص القدرة على
with the brain in its language, and
التواصل مع الدماغ و لغته الخاصة
the potential power of being able to do that.
والقدرة الكامنة في قدرتنا على ذلك
So it's different from the motor prosthetics
ان الامر مختلف عن المحركات الصناعية
where you're communicating from the brain
التي تقوم بنقل معلومات من دماغك
to a device. Here we have to communicate
الى عضو صناعي .. فهنا علينا ان نتواصل
from the outside world
من الخارج الى الداخل
into the brain and be understood,
وعلى الدماغ فهم هذا التواصل
and be understood by the brain.
فهماً جلياً
And then the last thing I wanted
ومن ثم اخر شيء
to say, really, is to emphasize
اريد ان اقوله هو التاكيد
that the idea generalizes.
على ان هذه الفكرة يمكن تعميمها
So the same strategy that we used
ويمكن لهذه الاستراتيحية التي نستخدم
to find the code for the retina we can also
لمعرفة شفرات الشبكية
use to find the code for other areas,
ان تستخدم لمعرفة باقي المناطق
for example, the auditory system and
الجهاز السمعي على سبيل المثال
the motor system, so for treating deafness
والجهاز الحركي .. اي يمكن معالجة الصُم
and for motor disorders.
ومعالجة الاضطرابات الحركية
So just the same way that we were able to
بذات الطريقة التي تمكنا منها بالقفز
jump over the damaged
فوق اعطاب
circuitry in the retina to get to the retina's
الشبكية والوصول الى الخلايا
output cells, we can jump over the
البصرية ,, يمكننا ايضا القفز
damaged circuitry in the cochlea
فوق قوقعة الاذن المعطوبة
to get the auditory nerve,
لكي نصل الى العصب السمعي
or jump over damaged areas in the cortex,
ويمكننا القفز من فوق اجزاء القشرة الدماغية المعطوبة
in the motor cortex, to bridge the gap
الى الجهاز الحركي و من ثم نعيد وصل الجسور العصبية
produced by a stroke.
بواسطة الصدمات
I just want to end with a simple
واريد ان انهي هذه المحادثة
message that understanding the code
برسالة بسيطة مفادها ان فهم الشفرة
is really, really important, and if we
هو امر فعلا مهم جداً
can understand the code,
وان استطعنا فهم الشفرة
the language of the brain, things become
ولغة الدماغ فان الامور
possible that didn't seem obviously
المستحيلة سوف تغدو ممكنة
possible before. Thank you.
والتي لم تكن كذلك من ذي قبل
(Applause)
تصفيق